Hey everybody, welcome back.
Let's try and solve that puzzle now, huh?
I think I got it now.
Take me to the cemetery.
Okay, so...
Let's have a look then.
Maybe this will give me a clue as well to the remaining words.
That's like the real puzzle for me right now, you know?
So this one is already facing the right way, I think.
So, God looks at instruments.
The preacher looks at... was it God?
I think so, but let's just double check.
No, the preacher talks to the man, okay.
And the man is over there.
Oh wait, the preacher is over here, of course.
That is the devotee.
You need to talk to the man.
There you go.
Now, the man talks to the devotee, I think, wasn't that it?
Yeah, he looks at the devotee.
Oh, I had them angled in the worst possible way here.
Like that.
And now this guy speaks to God, or he looks at God, right?
The preacher talks to the...
No, no, sorry.
The devotee looks at God, alright.
So, God is in the center.
Yes!
Wonderful!
What is hiding down here?
Oh, wait a minute.
Oh, the light!
Okay.
Smart.
You're so resourceful.
What do we have here?
Love the style of graphics, man.
Okay.
That's an empty room.
Oh, God, I'm gonna get so lost in here.
I can tell you that already.
I'm sticking to one angle here, meaning I always go right.
Oh, there's someone dead down here!
The preacher!
No!
Hold up a minute.
Maybe it means below, I'm going below.
Because he went below, right?
I'm not sure.
Interesting.
Well, that's unfortunate.
I guess he got lost in this labyrinth.
Or maze.
Keep going, right?
Look at these pipes over here.
Ooh!
What does that do?
It stopped the flow of water.
So, perhaps I can pass in that room I was in previously.
That's blocked off.
Okay.
Back out we go.
Where does this pipe lead?
I'm assuming it leads towards the place I was in before.
Let's follow the pipe.
Oh, yeah, of course it does.
And look, the leak has stopped.
Neat.
Ooh, so sneaky!
Look at that!
All right!
Whoa!
God, that looks so beautiful!
Look at this!
That's lovely.
Go.
Oh, my God.
Go through the door over there.
There's multiple doors here, it seems.
Oh, wow, this looks so different!
Really, I can go that way?
What the hell?
Wow, this is not what I was expecting at all!
What the...
Oh, God, please don't see me.
Look at that.
We got some more stuff.
Oh, man, this leads me to believe I'm done with this place, but I'm not!
What about the remaining things here?
Honestly, at this point, I just want to brute force it and see what the hell the answer was.
Is it that one?
It's not that one, either.
Instruments?
No, this is instruments for sure.
I think maybe barter could be the one here.
Toiling?
You're kidding!
Let's see what it actually says.
Make, create?
Oh!
That is so confusing.
So the guy was saying he made instruments.
He's not saying he's selling them.
Well, it's a shop!
Of course my first thought would be selling.
If I saw him making the instruments, then maybe, right?
What was I looking for now?
There was one other, this one.
Okay, so...
This, I don't know.
I gotta be honest.
I don't know any of these three.
This one...
I'm still gonna say this one means above.
Because we had the tower in the mural, right?
And where was the sun located?
Up above, right?
It was up top.
Go up.
Now this guy...
I don't know, we're gonna brute force this one.
Not like that.
Okay, let's fucking see what it says!
You've completed the translation of the devotee's language.
Hell yeah!
But I need to see what it says!
Oh, what's happening there?
I just got elevated.
In status.
Up, great!
Not...
free.
I would never have guessed this.
Well, I got up, I guess, at one point.
I mean, at first I thought this meant stop.
He's like, Halt, you know?
Barter made so much sense here, though.
He's saying, no, no, no, I want five bushels.
This one, though?
Dude, I...
I want to go back and see what those people were actually saying.
Because I still cannot comprehend what they possibly...
could be saying, even with this knowledge.
I need to see the conversations.
Okay, I obviously don't want to go down there.
They're gonna see me and be angry.
Um, let's have a look at this up here.
I see where we're going with this.
So we have the language of the devotees.
We're gonna have the language of the soldiers.
We're gonna have the language of maybe men.
But I would assume that would be the bottom part of...
of the tower.
Now, the top is obviously gonna be the language of the gods.
Something like that, at least.
Okay, we got some new symbols here.
Whoa!
Oh, there we go.
I thought we just got a whole book full of symbols.
Okay.
The door is closed.
I think that's what he said in the beginning, but who knows.
Um, I need to replay this conversation down here, first of all.
So he said...
soldiers coming up, right?
The...
something.
I'm very unsure about that, by the way.
Alright.
And then he's saying...
I don't know what he's saying.
Door is open?
Probably not.
He's talking to soldiers marching, right?
Let's move on.
What if I actually go down there?
What's gonna happen?
I gotta take a look at this.
Oh, I'm in sneak mode.
Oh, shit!
Oh, crap!
Run!
Go, go, go, go!
Through the crack!
Ha, ha, ha!
I made it!
Okay, hold on, hold on, hold on.
I see this thing over here.
I got to go back to the other place and see those conversations.
I cannot wait to see what they were saying.
Take me to, I believe, this one.
There we are.
Okay, take me up here now.
Let's see.
You!
I can't wait for this.
Don't go to the door.
The warriors locked the door.
Originally, though, it said...
You...
must...
slash need is what I thought it said, I think.
Go to door.
Or eye.
Maybe this means eye.
No, no.
Don't go to the door.
What about this, though?
Hmm.
Yeah, that was not obvious to me at all.
That one was hella difficult.
Now, you, what were you saying?
Yeah, what are you saying?
God above?
God is on high?
Maybe I was correct in saying he's expressing God's above.
You know?
Or maybe he's literal here and saying, God is up there, you know, at the very top.
You gotta go up.
I wanna go up.
Warriors are not devotees.
Warriors lock the door.
So he's unhappy with the fact that...
the warriors locked them off from ascending the tower.
I mean...
Okay.
I would never have guessed this.
Not in a million years.
Perhaps I'm just too stupid for that, actually.
Alright, let's go back up then.
Very interesting, uh...
changing colors here in the second level.
And what's with these...
things here?
You helped me?
Plants are dying?
I don't want plants to die.
Okay, that kinda makes sense in hindsight now.
But I would never have guessed this.
Never.
Alright, then.
But why is that even a part of this sort of display here?
Why is that, actually?
Why is that a part of this?
Why am I able to talk to this dude?
Is there something special going on with...
the gardener?
And why is this blinking right here?
I want to go back to the gardener.
I want to see if there's something going on with him.
Like, why else would he be...
in a zoom call there, saying that?
Perhaps I can help him with his plants.
Somehow.
Oh wait, I could have just teleported up to the other level.
Ah, whatever.
I'm gonna quickly throw this rock.
Oh, just a bump!
Oh, that was close.
Go investigate.
Let's go, buddy.
There we are.
Okay, up.
Good stuff.
Oh, and this one?
What were you saying, you little rascal?
We can't go up.
The devotee closed the door.
Let's seek the key.
Okay, that makes sense now.
Yeah, if I miss this one...
and that one, it's gonna be really difficult to solve.
For sure.
And what are you saying now?
You found the key.
We are free!
Yeah, again, never would have guessed that.
It just doesn't make any sense in this context to say that.
At least not for me.
But I'm also not a native English speaker, so maybe I'm not familiar with those expressions.
Um...
Like, I would imagine you would say we're free if you escape a cell with a key.
Not if you open a door to somewhere you want to go.
You know?
Um...
What was I doing?
Oh yeah, garden.
You!
You're the one on the speaker phone!
Preacher's not in the garden.
I can't find the preacher.
Plants are dying.
I don't like dying plants.
Yeah, alright, dude.
Alright, dude.
So, what is it about this guy?
Can I not do anything special with him?
Why are you on the speaker phone?
That's very weird to me.
Alright.
I'm gonna take the teleporter.
And get the hell out of dodge.
Up to the next level.
So, I imagine that the guardian, or soldier...
Was saying, the door is closed.
There were four words, I believe, in what he was saying.
And that's the only thing that sort of makes sense, right?
He's like, you cannot...
Or maybe he says, you cannot pass.
But that is...
Four words and not is...
Yeah, I'm not sure, actually.
Let me take another look at my stuff here.
The door is closed.
And then I got some new stuff up here.
Do we have any repeating ones?
I just wanna quickly see that again.
So, he's saying the...
Okay, so this one is the same.
What would he be saying here with three words?
Guys, follow me.
Or...
Turn left here.
If this is you, it would make sense with him talking to these people over here.
And it would also make sense for the guard up top, or down below, to say, you cannot enter.
Right?
Both are saying you.
So maybe this line means you.
These lines remind me a lot of the language in Tunic, actually.
Just a bit, I guess.
And what if this means God?
It has sort of the same feel to it, the shape at least.
Maybe you.
Not entirely sure on that.
And then he's saying something else.
He's saying...
He puts his hand down.
Okay.
Maybe gate?
Eh, I'm not sure.
Maybe you follow me.
Could be a thing he's saying.
Let's just go investigate some more.
What about this one?
A shield and a spear, it seems like.
Yeah.
Oh, what's this?
Warriors don't like death.
Death loves warriors.
That's actually a pretty deep sentence, if you think about it.
Only three words, and it says so much.
One, two, three, four, five.
Am I just gonna directly translate here?
Warriors don't like death?
Warriors don't like death, but that is like...
Ah, but hold on.
One, two, three, four, five.
There's two of these here because it's plural, right?
What about this one down here?
Death loves warriors.
Death...
...loves warriors.
See here, this is the same symbol as that symbol.
And that's the same symbol as that.
Maybe it's opposite?
Nah, not sure.
Warriors don't like death.
We got some new ones there.
Do we have any other repeating?
This one is repeating.
Warriors don't like death.
Death loves warriors.
So this one definitely means death.
That's what I'm thinking.
Death on that one, right?
And...
Ah, wait a second, maybe this guy in front of that...
...signifies plural.
You see that?
Warriors plural?
Oh...
This one is...
...plural, I guess.
And this one is...
...warriors.
In this case, warrior.
It could also be the, actually.
The warrior.
No.
This here.
Warriors don't like death?
This means don't.
Don't?
Okay.
Or maybe not.
Maybe it means not, as in, you know...
...the equivalent.
And this means like.
Plural, plural warrior don't like death.
Death likes warriors.
Or loves warriors.
I guess love would be better up here.
Love or like, right?
That's the thing.
Love or like.
Yeah.
For sure.
So now that we know...
Oh, there's also a spear here.
Oh!
No way, am I gonna do combat?
Some glyphs can be linked to the equivalent glyph of another language.
Even if it's not yet translated.
Right!
Okay.
Love like, I know what that is.
It is possible to validate the link from one glyph to another without having translated the original one yet.
Interesting.
Okay.
This is death.
What did I note down as death?
This one.
This one is not.
You know what?
I bet.
The opposite of not is just gonna be a square without the thing through it.
Like the strike through, you know?
Love and like.
Is that one.
And warrior is that one.
Heck yeah!
That's amazing.
Death, not, warrior, and love.
Yeah!
Fantastic.
Cool.
Very nice.
Okay, let's go this way.
Now I have a spear.
Am I actually gonna kill someone?
There's no way, right?
I love the color palette here too.
It's way more... I don't know.
Scary.
I don't think... Oh, what's that?
Whoa!
You are strong!
Holy shit!
Wow!
Get up there.
Uh oh, I hear marching.
Yo!
Sweet.
Reminds me a little bit of Inside by Playdead.
If you know, you know.
I'm on a proper adventure here.
Ha ha!
These are the same people I think I saw in the very beginning.
When I entered here.
He's saying, halt!
Warrior, stop!
Continue, stop.
March.
Okay.
So here he's saying, attention.
One guy towards the others.
Excuse me?
Okay, that one is not clear to me at all.
I gotta see that one again.
He's saying, the warriors.
Or he's just saying, warriors, stop.
Or halt.
Let's say that's halt.
Stop slash halt.
And then he's doing the other one.
Warriors, march.
Or continue.
Plural.
The doors...
are not.
I'm trying to link this to what the guy in the very first area said.
I thought he said the door is closed.
But we know he's saying, the doors...
are not something.
Open?
The doors are not traversable.
Which would fit with this guy saying, warriors, traverse.
Or warriors, march.
Carry on.
Continue.
Let's see here.
The doors are not...
travelable?
That's not a word, is it?
Passable.
Hm.
Yeah, march is wrong for sure, but I'm just gonna, you know...
approximately somewhere like that.
So, whatever it is, it's here.
Now this one is halt.
This one...
could mean...
I'm not sure about that one.
So he's saying those two things and nothing else.
Oh, what's this?
Oh, we got something else there.
Warrior?
Something.
Door?
I think the door is wrong.
No, door is right.
Maybe.
Actually, that one I'm not sure about.
What is this depicting?
Warriors are...
looking up to the sky.
Whoa, what is this?
They're carrying something on their shoulders.
Warriors holding up everything else.
Oh man, everything is so scary here.
Warriors halt.
Warriors...
follow maybe.
Not sure about that one.
What is that symbolize this drawing here?
One guy...
goes towards a pack of other guys?
What is that supposed to mean?
Join?
Meetup?
Stay in formation?
So by the way, notice how this one, continue slash march and stop?
Or like commands?
Right?
And they're all made of the same sort of symbol where there's a line going down into like a...
almost an arrow.
You see that?
Line going down into an arrow.
So I think this is also a command.
Here he's saying stop.
Here he's saying march.
And what is this one?
I think it's the... whatever it is, it's this one.
Because it's the same sort of shape.
And I'm wrong.
So never mind.
I thought they would be related.
Okay, I am not sure about that.
Oh, whoa, whoa, whoa, whoa, what's this?
Oh!
That has to mean God or something.
Just based on the God symbol from here.
You see that?
God is like this sort of diamond shape.
It looks very similar.
Then again, maybe these guys don't praise God or the Son.
Maybe they praise this dude.
The lead warrior.
The head honcho.
Whatever his name is.
This does look very totalitarian, doesn't it?
The whole regime here.
So it wouldn't surprise me if they had some sort of corrupt leader.
And this is what this is symbolizing.
Do you know what I mean?
And these are the slaves holding up the empire or something.
I'm definitely thinking of the empire from Star Wars right now, a little bit.
Oh, look at that lizard!
Oh man, what a camera angle.
Let's go.
In very dangerous territory here.
Oh, I actually went down here.
Isn't that a little risky?
Is that a good idea?
Yeah.
And he marches on.
I mean, this picture could sort of signify a leader to these men.
But wouldn't the arrow point the other way if they're following him?
Here it looks like he's following them.
Weird.
So many things to click on.
There's another door over here.
And two doors down below.
Let's not forget that.
Oh God, a torture device?
What is this?
What does that do?
Should I really be playing with things I don't understand?
Nothing happens.
What about this thing?
Hahaha, hamster wheel?
You're kidding.
All right.
What about now?
Oh!
It rotated.
No fucking way.
This guy's playing music up there.
Whoa!
Okay.
Something, something.
This is obviously a warrior.
Who is this dude?
Someone holding up a big stone.
And then there's a guy up here playing music.
And he has this halo on his head as well.
Try to do it again.
Oh, I gotta run the hamster wheel again.
Flip the switch!
This is the head honcho.
Is this simply another word for devotees and...
men?
I think this is God.
Let's put God in there.
So we have warriors above that.
What would that be?
If they see God as higher standing...
warrior...
something God.
This is God.
He's holding up this massive block.
For now, I'm just gonna put this middle guy as a devotee, because that's the only thing I know.
Or a man.
It could be either, I guess.
Warrior devotee.
Okay, okay, let me just...
turn this once more.
Aha!
I made a note.
Ah, that's actually nice, so I don't have to turn it every time.
Warrior...
something...
Okay.
This one says...
So they all start with warrior.
Warrior?
This one has to be God.
God slash leader of the... whatever outfit these guys are running, right?
Oh man, this one is difficult.
I'm not sure about this one.
I'm thinking...
It's like a hierarchy, right?
Warrior below God?
Maybe.
And then here we have...
warrior above men.
And here we have warrior...
Not sure about that one.
And I'm not sure about that one.
Let's just leave it for now.
Aha!
There's more.
Where does this come from?
Oh, that's messed up.
Look at these little demons.
An angel?
Heaven and hell?
What is he doing?
He's protecting these people.
This could mean protect...
whatever it is.
Where does this even come from?
I don't understand this.
Why did I note that down?
Mega confused!
But that's okay.
Let's see what else we got down here.
Go this way.
Uh oh.
We got a couple options here.
There's a door on the left.
I think I may need to...
follow this guy around.
Can I walk upstairs?
I can.
Go, go, go.
Oh shit!
Ah, they saw me.
Run!
Oh crap!
Get out of here!
Ah, there's... no!
Oh crap.
Okay, I think I gotta follow them.
That's the best way to do this.
Stay low.
Just like that.
How am I gonna get past these dudes though?
Maybe I'll find a rock somewhere.
A stone to throw.
And go.
Yes.
Very good.
Now go.
What?
You saw me?
No!
What?
How do you see me?
I guess the only way to do this...
is to go up here...
and then make a ro...
But there's a guy coming through that door immediately.
That's not happening.
Hmm.
Let me try and go back again.
Perhaps I missed an item of some sort.
Something that will distract them.
Maybe I can throw another rock.
You know?
Hit a gong.
Lizard!
I missed the cats though.
Oh!
Wait a minute!
I forgot about this in the first level.
Oh crap!
What is this water?
Why is it red?
Hopefully it's not blood.
What is happening here?
I think I gotta go this way.
Not seeing another option.
Now to get past these dudes up here and through that door.
Not sure about that.
If I go up here, he immediately sees me.
Yeah.
Oh!
They're coming from all directions!
Oh, you know what?
Maybe the guy only appears over there...
when I'm detected.
And if I'm not detected, I can go through.
I thought no matter what, that would be a guy at the door.
Okay, so here's the plan.
We're gonna go behind this guy.
As soon as the opportunity presents itself, we're gonna go now.
Go, go, go!
Quick, quick, quick, quick, quick, quick, quick!
Hurry!
Close one.
Oh, shit.
Oh, wow.
Stay quiet.
Go.
Look at the moon!
Remember the drawing on the bottom?
Oh, but how am I gonna...
Oh...
Wait a minute, this...
Oh, I missed my opportunity!
I see what's happening.
I need to walk behind the soldiers...
so they don't see me.
Do we have more soldiers coming in?
Are they walking back again?
Here we go, here we go, here we go.
That's it.
As soon as they pass in front, I'm gonna use them as cover.
Very sneaky.
Let's be ready.
And go.
Yes!
Should I really bang that gong?
That seems like a bad idea.
Oh, crap.
Go!
Holy crap.
Go, go, go, go, go!
Shit!
Close one.
What are you saying?
Warriors, go.
Oh, man, these guys are so evil!
The evilest of evil.
Oh, no.
I know what to do.
I gotta stay behind them now when these guys are coming.
Come on, then.
Hopefully I can just click on this door and he will automatically run there.
Go!
No, what are you doing, you idiot?
Why did you run into him?
You dumbass!
Go, go, go!
Close one.
Okay, that's definitely wrong.
He's saying...
Okay.
Put down box.
Warrior.
Oh, my God.
Uh...
Place, box, lift box.
Okay, by the way, where am I?
Oh, I'm up here.
I see.
I feel like I gotta see that interaction again.
This is so cool looking, though.
How do I see that interaction again?
Ah, we got more coming in.
Okay, let's see now.
Take a good look at this.
He's saying, Warrior, stop.
Now he's saying something, grab the box.
Or... lift.
He's saying three things.
Devotee.
I think this one is wrong.
With the Devotee.
This one I'm not sure about at all.
He is saying...
I don't know what he's saying.
What is he saying?
He's pointing at a box.
And then they walk over there.
Pick up box, maybe.
Let's just guess that for now.
Pick.
Up.
And box.
Pick up box.
He has it.
Then he says...
Maybe first, second and third box?
Pick first, pick second box?
Which would mean that this one is...
Where's the one I just had?
It was...
Oh god, I can't find it.
Oh, up.
First?
Maybe he's saying take... box.
That makes more sense, I guess.
Take slash grab, right?
Grab second box?
And then he's saying what?
Grab first box again?
Oh, small and big, I see.
I see the size of the box.
That is so smart.
Okay, okay, okay.
Small.
Right?
And big.
March...
He's saying march over here?
And then he's saying place boxes.
Put down boxes, right?
I'm going to say place.
Because put down is two words.
But, you know.
Place.
So this one is obviously that one.
This one is grab the box.
Now the last thing he's saying here...
Place boxes.
Boom.
And then he says warrior.
Uh...
Move boxes?
But there's no box symbol?
I don't know.
Whatever it is, it's either this symbol or that symbol that goes here.
That's what I can surmise.
So that guy...
So what is the actual word?
Push, okay.
I thought it would either be like drag or...
Maybe not slide, but push makes sense.
Transport, you know.
Yada yada.
Okay.
I think I prefer mine meaning place.
Lay is a little bit weird.
And then he says warrior push cart.
I think that means cart.
Wonderful.
There's one part I didn't quite understand is when he says...
Come over here, right?
And they walk over to the cart.
Is that what he's saying?
Walk to cart?
Warriors go cart?
Go cart!
Probably not.
I want to see this one more time.
I just want to see the part where he makes them come over to him.
And while that happens, I'm just going to walk around a bit.
There's an elevator.
They're surely not going to notice that.
I have a bad feeling about that, for sure.
Okay, let's see here now.
Warriors halt.
Yeah, that's good.
Grab big box.
Grab big box?
Two big boxes this time.
Last time it was one.
Grab small box.
He got the small box.
Wonderful.
Continue to cart.
Yeah, that actually makes complete sense.
Maybe it's just like go, you know, instead of continue.
That would make sense.
Stop and go is what you would say to soldiers, I guess.
Where's my go sign?
Let's just call this go.
What was the equivalent in the original language for go?
Wait, where's this?
Open.
Wasn't there a word for go?
Am I losing my mind?
Seek.
This one doesn't make sense.
Upslash great.
What?
Oh, go pass.
That's right.
Let's just call it go pass here as well.
I have a feeling it's going to be the same.
Which one was it?
Damn.
There we go.
Go slash pass.
That's it.
Now, we got to get on this lift here.
I guess I wait until these guys are done.
Otherwise, this dude will see me.
Yeah, better play safe here.
And I think I go now.
Oh, crap.
How are they not noticing me?
Oh, sweet.
Hey, look at this.
The river sticks.
Except it's not red.
Oh.
A guy putting down a box up there.
And we got more boxes in there.
Oh, shit.
Okay.
Where do I want to go?
He's going to see me, though.
There is no way.
Unless...
He's going to notice that.
How are you not...
a little bit baffled by that, huh?
I guess you could sort of pass now, but then he's going to turn.
Yeah, that doesn't work.
When he's walking that way, now I can exit and go like that.
That should be enough time.
Maybe.
Let me bring down that elevator again.
Also, there's writing up here.
What are these things?
Look like soda cups.
Oh, I can't do anything in there?
Okay.
What are they doing here?
Boxes?
Yeah, boxes.
What are these things?
I don't know what that is.
Cups?
They kind of look like sippy cups.
There's like little straws in them.
Maybe they like soda.
Big gulp, huh?
These guys are obsessed with boxes.
There's a red box there.
Really want to see what's in that.
Yes, and go.
Oh wait, I look like a worker now?
Is that the point?
Hide, hide, hide, hide, hide, hide, hide.
Oh, scary.
Oh, I get it.
We're going to stack the box in the elevator so we can hide behind it.
I see.
I get it now.
Look at that.
And then we can hide.
Okay.
Ah, I get that one.
Small, big.
This is a bottle.
A bottle.
Most likely.
And of course we got the box.
Boxes and bottles, huh?
That's what these soldiers are all about.
Maybe they're molotovs.
Bottle crate.
Okay.
Fancy, small and big, wonderful.
Now we had other stuff back here.
Right.
So this one.
I feel like I should have the answer to that one.
So what have I used?
Why can't I see the thing here?
Stop halt.
Go pass.
That's good.
Now this one.
Hmm.
It could simply mean leader.
This guy is a leader to men.
And I suspected that God here could be a leader.
I'm gonna try.
No, okay.
So I'm not sure about that one still.
Yeah, now I can hide there.
That's wonderful.
Take up the elevator.
Go.
Hide, hide, hide, hide, hide.
Now we wait.
I even blend in.
I could look like a box.
Kinda.
Go, go, go, go, go, go, go, go.
Oh, that was close.
Oh.
Oh, damn.
Look at this.
You know what?
Let's take a quick break and I'll see you in the next episode.
Bye-bye.